So you’ve just been asked two questions supposedly designed to assess your intelligence.
Bạn vừa được hỏi hai câu hỏi được tạo ra để đánh giá trí thông minh của bạn
What you should have hopefully noticed is that these questions were biased depending
Hi vọng là bạn nhận ra rằng những câu hỏi này là thiên vị dựa trên nền văn hóa bạn lớn lên
on the culture that you grew up in, or where exposed to via tv and other forms of media.
hoặc nơi tiếp xúc với TV và các phương tiện truyền thông
The first question asked you which of the following animals does not belong.
Câu hỏi đầu tiên hỏi bạn xem con vật nào không cùng nhóm
The kangaroo?
Kangaroo?
Dingo?
Chó Dingo?
Wombat?
Gấu túi?
Or is it the Platypus?
Hay thú mỏ vịt?
Well the answer is “platypus”.
Câu trả lời là thú mỏ vịt
It’s the only one there that lays eggs, it’s a monotreme.
Nó là loài duy nhất đẻ trứng, và là loài động vật đơn huyệt
Now this is an easier question if you’ve grown up in Australia learning about these
Đây sẽ là câu hỏi dễ nếu bạn lớn lên ở Úc và được học về những con vật này
animals.
animals.
The Platypus’s unusual characteristics are commonly taught at school.
Đặc điểm riêng biệt của thú mỏ vịt thường được dạy ở trường
Notice how I didn’t make a joke about any of those animals stealing babies?
Tôi không hề đùa về việc bất cứ con vật nào trong số trên đi ăn trộm con đúng không?
Now the second question, which was How many nickels are in a quarter?
Với câu hỏi thứ 2 "Bao nhiêu đồng 5 xen thì bằng một đồng 25 xen"
Well, here’s a quarter.
Đây là đồng 25 xen
That’s 25 cents in currency in the United States of a America.
Tức là nó có trị giá 25 xen ở Mỹ
And here’s a nickel.
Còn đây là đồng 5 xen
They’re worth 5 cents in the USA.
Trị giá 5 xen ở Mỹ
So the correct answer is 5.
Nên câu trả lời đúng là 5
If you are someone who is from Australia or another country outside of the USA, question
Nếu bạn là người Úc hoặc không phải người Mỹ
two may have appeared more difficult to answer compared to question one.
thì câu hỏi hai có vẻ khó hơn câu hỏi một
We don&#39;t use quarters in Australia.
Ở Úc không có đồng 25 xen
So, it’s a monetary system we&#39;re not familiar with.
Vì thế nên nó là một hệ thống tiền tệ lạ
Unless you grew up in the United States or spent some time there, you wouldn&#39;t necessarily
Trừ khi bạn lớn lên ở Mỹ hoặc từng sống ở đây thì bạn sẽ không quen với đồng 25 xen và 5 xen
be familiar with quarters and nickels.
be familiar with quarters and nickels.
In Canada, they have loonies and toonies.
Ở Canada họ có đồng loonie và toonie
Loonie refers to a Canadian one dollar coin and toonie refers to a Canadian two dollar
Loonie là đồng xu $1 ở Canada còn toonie là đồng $2
coin.
coin.
So we could have made this question easier for Canadians to answer and more difficult
Nên ta có thể biến câu hỏi là thành dễ dàng với người Canada và khó với mọi người khác
for everyone else.
for everyone else.
How well you do on these questions is largely a function of your culture not your intelligence.
Việc bạn trả lời được những câu hỏi này phần lớn dựa vào nền văn hóa của bạn chứ không phải trí tuệ
This is why the two questions from the previous activity are biased because they&#39;re not really
Đó là vì sao hai câu hỏi từ hoạt động trước được coi là thiên vị vì chúng không đánh giá trí tuệ
assessing intelligence.
assessing intelligence.
They’re assessing your cultural knowledge to a large extent.
Chúng đánh giá mức độ hiểu biết văn hóa của bạn